"So, tell us about your work?"

Well, I study clusters of galaxies. And in general, clusters are an important tool for doing high-prec cosmology because they are the yet largest baryonic manifestation of large scale structure growth. They also provide complementary, and most importantly, orthogonal constraints on the dark energy equation of state to techniques like CMB fluctuations, baryon accoustic oscillations, and high redshift supernovae surveys, which are geometric measures. The adiabatic model of hierarchical structure formation is well studied and this model robustly results in clusters which are self-similar. Self similarity is great because it provides a means for calculating mass directly from observables like temperature and luminosity. But observations have long shown that clusters are not scaled versions of each other and that at even smaller scales, like group or galaxy scale, the case is even worse (this is work by post-doc here, Ming Sun). The breaking of self-similarity results in broad dispersion in mean mass-scaling relations, which if not corrected for, will result in the over and under prediction of cluster masses.  This, of course, is very bad news for the holy grail of high-precision cluster cosmology: mass selected samples from SZ surveys. So this is where my work comes in...  The breaking of self similarity results from non-gravitational processes, such as radiative cooling, merger shocks, and the variety of shapes dark matter potentials have. I've researched extensively in two of these areas: mergers and cooling.

On the topic of mergers, I focused on finding a way to quantify the virialization state of clusters. The goal was to construct a metric which quantifies spatial and spectral variations of the ICM which are the result of cluster substructure. We could then use this metric to further reduce the scatter in mean mass-scaling relations, like Yx-M. Specifically I was looking for an aspect-independent measure of a cluster's dynamic state. And we found our inspiration in a 2001 paper by Matheson and Evrard where they analyzed an ensemble of cluster simulations. The simulations neglected cooling and feedback, but they still found some clusters were cool for their mass. Well they suggested that during a merger, cool spectroscopically unresolved accreting subclusters can result in band specific bias of integrated cluster temperature. And they suggested a study using Chandra to detect this temperature biasing by measuring hard-band and full-band temperatures and looking for a skew in their ratio. And that's what we did...

First, I scoured the chandra data archive for every cluster observation where a minimum of R5000 fit in the field of view. Then I spent two years working with the data! I measured soft and hard band temps, calculated their ratio, accounted for systematics (s/n, redshift effects, column dens, cross-calib w/ XMM), and looked fro trends. What I found was that clusters with large ratios of their hard and full band temperatures were correlated with non-cool core clusters. I also found that high temperature ratio clusters were mostly known mergers. So from a statistical standpoint this temperature ratio looks useful. Mark and his graduate student, David Ventimiglia, are following up my results with an NSF funded study of simulations by Steffano Borgani. They'll track temperature ratio over the lifetime of some clusters, and along with some other virialization measures, they see if the ratio helps in reducing scatter. I'm optimistic.


But that was a quote, unquote, small part of my thesis work. The cornerstone is my entropy project. The core region of some clusters has a cooling time shorter than a Hubble time. This results in prodigious cooling which in turn creates higher luminosity and lower temperatures at a given mass. The end result being even more intrinsic scatter in self-similar scaling relations. So to understand this scatter we must study the effects of cooling and any feedback which may result. Observations have long shown that core gas does not cool completely, well, not to less than one third the virial temperature anyway, something retards cooling in the core by heating the ICM. It's a widely accepted solution that heating of the ICM proceeds by AGN blown bubbles. And one way to understand AGN heating, and really feedback in general, is by studying the entropy distribution of the ICM.

Entropy as I define it is a fundamental property of the ICM, moreso than temperature and density alone. Temperature reflects the depth of the gravitational potential well, and heating or cooling of gas somply results in expansion and contraction of the gas within the well. Density on the other hand mainly reflects the wells capacity to compress that heated and cooled gas. But specific entropy determines the density at a given pressure [at constant pressure, d(enthalpy)/T=S]. So one can view the X-ray observables as manifestations of the dark matter halo's depth and shape, in addition to the strucutre of gas entropy. By studying entropy, one is studying the entire thermal history of the cluster.

My cornerstone project involves analyzing the entropy distributions for a Chandra archive limited sample of galaxy clusters. It rather straight forward: We measure radial temperature, surface brightness, derive deprojected electron density, and the calculate entropy as T divide by electron density to the two-thirds. We then fit a model which assumes an entropy pedestal at small radii and a power-law at large radii. I then took this massive library of entropy profiles and started digging.

We have quite a few results thus far. I've found that an entropy pedestal is a universal feature of clusters. That the central entropy distribution is bimodal. I've also found a strong relation between entropy and evidence of feedback.  If your a cluster, and your K0 is less than 20 keV cm**2, it means you have star formation in your BCG, and most likely have a radio-loud AGN. This is rather interesting because K0 equals 20 is the conductive stablity threshold. This is tantilizingly suggestive that feedback is regulated by conduction and that the uniform azimuthal distribution of energy, which has been so problematic, is aided by conduction. There are also lots of results: we're using K0 distribution to constrain the timescale of AGN feedback, there are entropy scaling relations which I haven't looked much at, we're looking now to see if we've observed evolution of cool cores as a function of redshift, and ultimately we want push classifying clusters based simply on their central entropy value.

"Tell us about the coupling of conduction to AGN feedback."
- there is a critical length scale below which thermal conduction smoothes out temperature inhomogeneities: the Field Length
- multiphase gas can only form in systems larger than this length scale
- take a gas cloud of radius r and set radiative losses via free-free cooling equal to Spitzer electron thermal conduction
- Field length: through a scaling conincidence, Field length is a function of entropy alone, lambda=K^(3/2)*sqrt(suppression)
- conduction solves the problem of transferring AGN feedback energy away from the bipolar outflow axes

"We'd like to know more about Elena's code and what it does. How do you plan to use it?"
- well, I misspoke and the code is more Alessandro Gardini's. It's the X-MAS software package
- Pick an emission model, APEC, MEKAL, Raymond-Smith, etc.
- A spectrum of emissivity is assigned to each gas particle or fluid element in the datacube
- Spatial images of the cluster differential flux are constructed by summing over the volumes of all of the particles
- These images are used, pixel by pixel, as input models to XSPEC, which creates photon spectra for the different pixels of the Chandra CCD detectors
- Thus information on direction and energy is preserved
- The photon events are then attached to the datacube
- Add background events and anything you wish (like a custom PSF)
- File format is identical to real observations from Chandra (use CIAO)
- X-MAS takes into account most of the physical characteristics of Chandra: ARF and RMF are fully reproduced

"What are your plans for future work?"
- for my independent research plan...
- solve bimodality w/ cycle 10 prop
- Spitzer-XMM archival project of SF in BCGs
- observational tests of ICM heating with bubbles
- understand low entropy systems w/o SF or AGN
- understand high entropy systems w/ AGN
- developing model for feedback regulation via conduction
- get into radio, ir, and optical analysis
- hopefully construct a strong resume and program to pursue prize fellowships (hubble, chandra, carnegie)
- very longterm I want to get a faculty position somewhere

"What do you want to accomplish as a post-doc?"
- resolve questions raised by my thesis
- illuminate the connection between feedback and conduction
- accomplish group specific goals

"What are the shortcomings of your work?"
- isolated, meaning no large collaboration or greater context
- lack of modeling to now: conduction

"Why do we need more sophisticated models of mergers?"
- simulations currently do not properly reproduce the entropy structure of real clusters
- entropy greater than 100 is difficult, if not impossible, to generate with AGN alone
- pre-heating is definitely part of the energy budget
- but soft mergers which create cold fronts may be important too...
- but sims currently lack the resolution to properly get feedback working or make cold fronts in a cosmo volume

Cold fronts:
- what are they?
	+ increase in dens and sb
	+ decrease in temp
	+ pressure continuity
	+ inverted behavior from shock fronts
- in a merger, the gas entropy can increase beyond the ambient entropy via shock heating
	+ this leads to convective instability
	+ this leads to hot underdense gas bubbles
	+ which lead to buoyant gas rising along grav. gradient (ie perp to merger axis)
- merge-o-meter for clusters
- uses:
	+ the width of the front is several times smaller than the Coulomb mean free path for electrons; this indicates that the thermal conduction must be suppressed, at least across the front
	+ the extent of the sharp boundary indicates Kelvin‐Helmholtz instabilities are partially suppressed, most likely by magnetic fields parallel to the boundary
	+ use the above to determine energy transport and magnetic field strength in ICM
	+ If the origin and properties of cold fronts are understood, they can provide powerful constraints on the frequency of cluster mergers and properties of the intracluster medium

Questions for them:
"What are you looking for in a candidate?"
"Will there be teaching requirements?"
"Where do post-docs from Swinburne typically head-off to?"
"What kind of travel, publication, and equipment funding is available?"
"What is the office space situation?"

Committee:
Warrick Couch:
- senior member of 2dF Galaxy Redshift Survey
- lead member of AAOmega "WiggleZ" Dark Energy Project
- Sarah Brough is his post-doc
	+ she works on BCG-environment connection
	+ she has radio experience (YAY!)

Chris Blake:
- WiggleZ is high-z BAO survey
- gal evolution
- cosmologist

Greg Poole:
- WiggleZ
- sims: gal cluster mergers, AGN, and jets

Michael Murphy:
- quasar abs lines

Gwyn Morgan:
- information, communication, and technologies faculty﻿﻿﻿
